Guide to the Brownsville and East New York photographs, 1958-1965 BCMS.0044
Brooklyn Collection
Brownsville and East New York photographs, 1958-1965
Brooklyn Collection
BCMS.0044
0.2 Linear Feet in 1 document box.
99 black and white photographic prints of the Brooklyn neighborhoods of Brownsville and East New York dated 1958-1965.
Scope and Contents
99 black and white photographic prints.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Provenance
Purchased from Brian Merlis in 2018.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series by neighborhood. Within each series, the photographs are arranged chronologically.
Historical Note
Brownsville and East New York are adjoining neighborhoods in the eastern part of Brooklyn, New York. While it can be difficult to definitively state the borders of neighborhoods, Brownsville is often roughly considered to be bounded by Eastern Parkway to the north, Ralph Avenue/E. 98th Street to the west, Linden Boulevard to the south, and the elevated subway tracks between Junius Street and Van Sinderen Avenue to the east. East New York's boundaries are roughly located at Cypress Hills Cemetery to the north, the elevated rail tracks next to Van Sinderen Avenue to the west, Jamaica Bay to the south, and the Queens County line to the east. The photos in this collection also include images of Ocean Hill, a smaller neighborhood to the north of Brownsville with which Brownsville is often associated.
Both of these neighborhoods experienced profound shifts during the period depicted in these photographs. In the early twentieth century, this part of Brooklyn was largely populated by working class European immigrants. Due to the development of several New York City Housing Authority (NYCHA) housing projects in both neighborhoods, as well as changing immigration policies in the United States, the neighborhood demographics shifted midcentury to primarily African-American and Hispanic residents.
The photos in this collection primarily depict street scenes, which often include distinctive vehicles such as buses or police cars. There are also images of the residents of these communities which give a glimpse of their demographic makeup. Many local businesses appear in these photographs as well.
Related Materials
Brooklyn Eagle photographs (BCMS.0002): multiple headings for Brownsville and East New York
Brooklyn ephemera collection (BCMS.0007): headings for Brownsville and East New York
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available on our digital collections.
Automobiles; Brownsville (New York, N.Y.); East New York (New York, N.Y.); Ocean Hill (New York, N.Y.); Photographs; Police vehicles; Streets
- Brownsville
  - Rockaway and Lott Avenues, 1958 April 21 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Newport Street between Amboy Street and Herzl Street, 1958 April 26; (2 photographs) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sutter Avenue from Thatford Avenue, 1958 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Pitkin Avenue west from Sackman Street, 1959 January 27 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chester Street from Riverdale Avenue, 1959 November 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Riverdale Avenue from Chester Street, 1959 November 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sackman Street between Pitkin and Belmont Avenues, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Thatford and Pitkin Avenues, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Feldman Lumber, Dumont and Hopkinson Avenues (now Thomas S. Boyland Street), 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Police car, Pitkin and Thatford Avenues, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Stone Avenue (now Mother Gaston Boulevard) south toward Pitkin Avenue, 1962 May 9; (2 photographs) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Stone Avenue (now Mother Gaston Boulevard) north to Pitkin Avenue, 1962 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chester Street between Pitkin and Sutter Avenues, 1962 May 13; (2 photographs) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dumont Avenue toward Chester Street, 1962 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Dumont Avenue and Chester Street, 1962 May 22 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Christopher and Lott Avenues, 1962 October 24; (3 photographs) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bristol Street toward Sutter Avenue, 1962 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Riverdale Avenue east from East 98th Street, 1962 December 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Police car, Blake Avenue to Strauss Street, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Blake Avenue to Strauss Street, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Police car, Chester Street to Blake Avenue, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Blake Avenue from Powell Street, 1963 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Blake Avenue and Powell Street, 1963 April 17; (2 photographs) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Powell Street from Blake Avenue, 1963 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Amboy Street toward Blake Avenue, 1963 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Junius Street to Sutter Avenue, 1963 April 26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sutter Avenue east toward Junius Street, 1963 April 26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Powell Street and Glenmore Avenue, 1963 July 30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Stone Avenue (now Mother Gaston Boulevard) south from Pitkin Avenue, 1963 September 7 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Pitkin Avenue east from Stone Avenue (now Mother Gaston Boulevard), 1963 September 7 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Rockaway Parkway south from East New York Avenue, 1963 September 8; (2 photographs) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Pitkin Avenue east from Stone Avenue (now Mother Gaston Boulevard), 1963 September 7 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Pitkin Avenue and Grafton Street/Zion Park, 1963 November 17; (4 photographs) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Newport Street from Saratoga Avenue, 1963 December 6 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Saratoga Avenue north from Newport Street, 1963 December 6 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Police car, Riverdale Avenue to Christopher Avenue, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Subway elevated tracks, Livonia Avenue and Chester Street, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Powell Street near Sutter Avenue, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Crowd at Dumont Avenue and Saratoga Avenue, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Saratoga Avenue north from Dumont Avenue, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Police car outside bowling alley, Linden Boulevard from Rockaway Avenue, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Feldman Lumber, Dumont Avenue and Hopkinson Avenue (now Thomas S. Boyland Street), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Christopher and Riverdale Avenues, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Powell Street and Glenmore Avenues, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dumont Avenue west to Hopkinson Avenue (now Thomas S. Boyland Street), 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bus outside P.S. 275, Rickaway Avenue and Linden Bouelvard, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Dumont Avenue west to Saratoga Avenue, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chester Street and Sutter Avenue, 1964 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Strauss Street to Dumont Avenue, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dumont Avenue west to Strauss Street, 1964 March 6 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Amboy Street near Sutter Avenue, 1964 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 121 Amboy Street, near Sutter Avenue, 1964 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Pitkin Avenue east to Hopkinson Avenue (now Thomas S. Boyland Street), 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dean Street and Howard Avenue, Ocean Hill, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Fulton Street and Rockway Avenue, Ocean Hill, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newport Street west to Saratoga Avenue, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newport Street east to Saratoga Avenue, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Pitkin and Stone Avenues (now Mother Gaston Boulevard), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lott Avenue west from Stone Avenue (now Mother Gaston Boulevard), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - P.S. 184, Lott and Stone Avenues (now Mother Gaston Boulevard), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Saratoga Avenue from Newport Street, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Riverdale Avenue south to Stone Avenue (now Mother Gaston Boulevard), 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - People on public housing bench, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Police car, Eastern Parkway and Sterling Place, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- East New York
  - Liberty Avenue and Wyona Street, 1958 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Liberty Avenue and Chestnut Street, 1958 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Essex Street to Dumont Avenue, 1958 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Essex Street between Liberty and Atlantic Avenues, 1958 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Liberty Avenue west to Hinsdale Street, 1958 June 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Vermont Street and Belmont Avenue, 1959 January 11 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Crescent and Fulton Streets, 1959 April 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Blake Avenue and Essex Street, 1959 April 29 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Glenmore Avenue west to Ashford Street, 1959 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Jerome Street to Pitkin Avenue, 1959 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Pennsylvania and Riverdale Avenues, 1959 November 14 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Man at Vermont Street and Stanley Avenue, 1962 May 13 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Vermont Street near Atlantic Avenue, 1962 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Alabama Avenue from Riverdale Avenue, 1962 October 24 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Alabama Avenue to Riverdale Avenue, 1962 October 24 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Montauk Avenue to Pitkin Avenue, 1963 July 2 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Arlington Avenue to Jerome Street, 1963 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ridgewood Avenue at Force Tube Avenue, 1964 January 10 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Jamaica Avenue west to Force Tube Avenue, 1964 January 10 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Belmont Avenue toward Hemlock Street, 1964 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hemlock Street toward Belmont Avenue, 1964 February 15 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sutter Avenue east from Van Sinderen Avenue, 1964 February 26 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Jamaica Avenue east to Miller Avenue, 1964 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Synagogue, Alabama Avenue north to Dumont Avenue, 1964 July 28 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Fortunoff's, Alabama Avenue at Livonia Avenue, 1964 July 28 (Box 1, Folder 13)